# **Mohammad Sabik Irbaz**

LinkedIn: linkedin.com/in/sabik-irbaz/
Portfolio: msi1427.github.io/
GitHub: github.com/msi1427

Twitter: twitter.com/msi\_bertman
Email: sabikirbaz@iut-dhaka.edu
Phone: +8801623848732

Last updated December 7, 2021

I am a Data Scientist at Leadbook Pte. Ltd. I am currently working with Dr. Md. Ruhul Amin from Fordham University on data-driven Social NLP problems. I used to work as a Lead ML Engineer at Omdena Inc. and Pioneer Alpha Ltd. where I have led several ML projects from research, development to production. During my four years of undergraduate studies, I was immensely fortunate to be advised by Dr. Md. Kamrul Hasan and Dr. Hasan Mahmud where I have mostly worked on Text Style Transfer (TST), Clinical ML, and Data-centric AI.

## **Research Interests**

I am primarily excited in Natural Language Processing (NLP), Artifical Intelligence (AI) and Data Science research. My research interests include:

- Efficient modeling, benchmarking, evaluation and robustness in NLP [P5, P6]
- Annotating and cleaning datasets with minimal cost [P5, P8]
- Fact verification using historical data [P7]
- Explainable, Interpretable, and Reproducible AI
- Low-resource and Multilingual NLP [P3, P4]
- AI for Good (Social, Clinical & Other Disciplines) [P1, P2, P5, P6, P7]

#### Education

## Islamic University of Technology(IUT)

Dhaka, Bangladesh

B.Sc. in Computer Science and Engineering (CSE)

Jan, 2017 - Mar, 2021

**CGPA**: 3.44/4.00

**Dissertation:** "Medical Expertise Style Transfer using Denoising Autoencoders" [Thesis Book] [Presentation]

GPA: **5.00**/5.00

GPA: 5.00/5.00

Supervisor: Dr. Md. Kamrul Hasan, Professor, Department of CSE, IUT

Notre Dame College(NDC)

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Higher Secondary Certificate (HSC), 2016

Jul, 2014 - Dec, 2016

Cox's Bazar Government High School

Cox's Bazar, Bangladesh

Secondary Secondary Certificate (SSC), 2014

Jan, 2009 - Dec, 2013

## **Research Experience**

 $\{^{\alpha}$  primary contributor;  $^{\beta}$  secondary contributor;  $^{\gamma}$  supervisor $\}$ 

## Fordham Human Centered AI Research Lab

Mar, 2021 - Present

Department of CIS, Fordham University, New York, USA

Advisor(s): Dr. Md. Ruhul Amin

- (1) <sup>\alpha</sup>COVID-19 Public Policy Conformity Analysis NLP, Data Extraction, Topic Modeling, NLI, EDA [P7]
- (2) <sup>\alpha</sup> Mitigating Social Bias in NLP NLP, Explainability, Text Style Transfer

#### **Computer Vision Lab (CVLab)**

Nov, 2020 - Present

Department of CSE, IUT, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Advisor(s): Sabbir Ahmed

- (1) <sup>\alpha</sup> Automatic Radiology Report Generation *NLP, Image Captioning, Image Segmentation* [Report]
- (2) <sup>7</sup>Data-centric Approach for Explainabile Text Classification NLP, Active Learning, Explainability
- (3) \(^1\)Logical Reasoning QA using Standardized Test Questions NLP, QA, CSR, Data Collection, NLI

## Systems and Software Lab (SSL)

Jul, 2019 - Present

Department of CSE, IUT, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Advisor(s): Dr. Md. Kamrul Hasan, Dr. Hasan Mahmud

- (1) <sup>\beta</sup> Automated wheelchairs for semi-paralyzed patients. Signal Processing, ML, Adruino
- (2) <sup>\alpha</sup> Medical Expertise Text Style Transfer NLP, Active Learning, Text Style Transfer [P5, P6]
- (3) <sup>a</sup>Efficient Active Learning Approach for Data Annotation ML, Active Learning, Data Annotation [P8]

- (4) Query-focused Multi-Document Text Summarization for Bangla NLP, Low-resource QA, Summarization
- (5) <sup>α</sup>Trustworthy NLP *NLP*, *Out-of-domain Data Filtering*

## **Publications**

More updated list here or Google Scholar {\*equal contribution, <sup>c</sup>corresponding author}

- [P8] Mohammad Sabik Irbaz, Raian Rahman, Hasan Mahmud, and Md. Kamrul Hasan<sup>c</sup>. "Efficient Active **Learning Approach for Data Annotation**". *Manuscript in Preparation*.
- [P7] Mohammad Sabik Irbaz, Md. Ruhul Amin<sup>c</sup>, Rupak Sarkar, and Ashiqur R. KhudaBukhsh. "COVID-19 **Public Policy Conformity Analysis"**. *Manuscript in Preparation*. [Presentation]
- [P6] Mohammad Sabik Irbaz, Abir Azad, Raian Rahman, Hasan Mahmud, and Md. Kamrul Hasan<sup>c</sup>. "Medical **Expertise Style Transfer using Denoising Autoencoders**". *Manuscript in Preparation*. [Book]
- [P5] Mohammad Sabik Irbaz, Abir Azad, Zarif Ahmed, Md. Ashfaq Raiyan, Raian Rahman, Hasan Mahmud, and Md. Kamrul Hasan<sup>c</sup>. "c-MSD: A Curated Dataset for Medical Expertise Style Transfer using Active Learning Approach". Under Review.
- [P4] Alif Ashrafee\*, Akib Mohammed Khan\*, Mohammad Sabik Irbazc, and MD Abdullah Al Nasim. "Realtime Bangla License Plate Recognition Pipeline for Low Resource Video-based Applications". Real-World Surveillance: Applications and Challenges Workshop, collocated with IEEE/CVF WACV 2022 [Presentation] [Poster]
- [P3] Fahim Shahriar Khan, Mueeze Al Mushabbir, Mohammad Sabik Irbaz<sup>c</sup>, and MD Abdullah Al Nasim. "End-to-End Natural Language Understanding Pipeline for Bangla Conversational Agents". Proceedings of the 20<sup>th</sup> IEEE International Conference on Machine Learning and Applications, 2022 [Presentation]
- [P2] Mohammad Sabik Irbaz<sup>c</sup>, MD Abdullah Al Nasim, and Refat E Ferdous. "Real-Time Face Recognition System for Remote Employee Tracking". Proceedings of the International Conference on Big Data, IoT, and Machine Learning, 2022. Springer, Singapore.
- [P1] Mohammad Sabik Irbaz\*, Abir Azad\*, Tanjila Alam Sathi, and Lutfun Nahar Lota<sup>c</sup>. "Nurse Care Activity Recognition Based on Machine Learning Techniques Using Accelerometer Data". Proceedings of the 8th International Workshop on Human Activity Sensing Corpus and Applications, collocated with ACM UbiComp/ISWC 2020 [DOI] [Presentation]

## **Industrial Experience**

Leadbook Pte. Ltd. Singapore

**Data Scientist** 

Dec, 2021 - Present

We have millions of contacts in our database. An important problem is to cluster contact job titles into categories in an unsupervised or semi-supervised manner. Most of my works involve improving and maintaining this pipeline. The project involves — NLP, Data Cleaning, Clustering, Phrase Similarity [Code]

Omdena Inc. New York, USA

## Lead Machine Learning Engineer

Apr, 2021 - Jun, 2021

Collaborated with 50 ML and data engineers from 20 countries on Equilo Project - Building Gender Equality Assessment Functionality using NLP. This large scale work was divided into 7 major tasks. I was the task leader of the team building the recommender system for the organizations with low gender equality scores. I also lead the team building the web app and deploying the whole data and ML pipeline to GCP.

This project involved — Scraping, NLP, GCP, Firestore, Django, ReactJS, StreamLit, Cloud SQL [Article]

## Pioneer Alpha Ltd. Lead Machine Learning Engineer

Dhaka, Bangladesh Jan, 2021 - Oct, 2021

- Supervised and delivered the following core projects successfully to the corresponding clients:
- (1) Multilingual Chatbot as Business Assistant NLP, NLU, Low-resource, Tensorflow, Rasa, Flask [P3] (2) Low-resource Bangla License Plate Detection and Recognition — OCR, Tensorflow, OCR, Flask [P4]

- (3) Face Detection and Recognition for Remote Office Vision, OpenCV, dlib, Flask [P2]
- (4) Trello Automation for Directed Premiere Video Editing Vision, OpenCV, dlib, Adobe Premiere, Trello [Code]

#### Nascenia Ltd.

#### Software Engineer, Intern

Dhaka, Bangladesh Nov, 2019 - Jan, 2020

Worked on a large-scale government project on VAT automation, Project Uddogi

This project involved — Ruby on Rails, HTML, CSS, Heroku [Article]

## **Teaching Experience**

#### Amar iSchool

Dhaka, Bangladesh Mar, 2021 - Dec, 2021

#### **Head Course Instructor**

Applied Data Science and Machine Learning — [Course Repository]

Our prime goal is to empower the local ML enthusiasts with a limited background CS and Mathematics.

- Taught data science and machine learning for production
- Gave 15 lectures, all self-developed
- Developed course assignments and projects

## **Selected Projects**

An exhaustive list can be found here

- (1) Medical Expertise Style Transfer System for Layman Patients PyTorch, Fastai, Flask [Code]
- (2) Multimodal Multi-label Genre Classifier PyTorch, Fastai, Numpy, Pandas [Code]
- (3) Anime vs Animation vs CGI PyTorch, Fastai, Flask [Code]
- (4) Original Transformer for Bengali Translation PyTorch [Code]

#### **Skills**

**Programming Language:** Python, C, C++, Ruby, Octave

Framework: Pytorch, fastai, Flask, Tensorflow, Keras, Ruby on Rails

Tools and Libraries: Git, LaTeX, Google Colab, HuggingFace, Google Cloud Platform

Languages: English, Bangla, Hindi, Arabic

#### **Selected Awards & Achievements**

An exhaustive list can be found here

- Won the OIC Scholarship that waived 75% of my undergraduate education costs (2% acceptance rate)
- Champion, 2nd Nurse Care Activity Recognition Challenge 2020. Won a trip to Japan. [P1]
- Finalist, AI For Bangla Challenge 2021 (among 147 teams) [P3]
- Runners Up, IUT Computer Programming Contest 2019 (among 77 teams)
- 2nd Runners Up, EDU Inter University Programming Contest 2020 (among 50 teams)

### **Extra-curricular Activities**

- Travelled across major locations in Bangladesh.
- Part of ML Discussion Groups: Fordham DS Research Group, Turing NLP Group
- Associate Member, Omdena AI Global Community
- Contest Judge, 16th December Programming Contest 2019
- Former Programming Instructor, IUT Programming Community
- Former Vice President, IUT Computer Society
- Assistant General Secretary, IUT 10th ICT Fest
- Volunteer Coordinator, IUT 9th ICT Fest
- Class and Batch Representative, IUT CSE Batch'16

#### References

Available upon request